I grew up in Bihar, India's poorest state,
نشأت في "بيهار" ، أفقر وﻻية في الهند ،
and I remember when I was six years old,
و أتذكر عندما كان عمري ست سنوات ،
I remember coming home one day to find a cart
أذكر عودتي إلى البيت أحد الأيام لأجد عربة
full of the most delicious sweets at our doorstep.
مليئة بأشهى أنواع الحلوى أمام البيت .
My brothers and I dug in,
هجمنا عليها أنا وإخوتي
and that's when my father came home.
و عندها عاد أبي إلى البيت.
He was livid, and I still remember how we cried
و غضب جداً ، و لا زلت أذكر كيف بكينا
when that cart with our half-eaten sweets
حين تلك العربة بحلوتنا النصف مأكولة
was pulled away from us.
نزعت من بين أيدينا
Later, I understood why my father got so upset.
لاحقاً، أدركت سبب غضب أبي،
Those sweets were a bribe
لقد كانت تلك الحلوى رشوة
from a contractor who was trying to get my father
من مقاول كان يحاول جعل أبي
to award him a government contract.
يكافئه بعقد حكومي.
My father was responsible for building roads in Bihar,
كان والدي مسؤلاً عن بناء الطرق في بيهار،
and he had developed a firm stance against corruption,
وكان موقفه صارماً ضد الفساد ،
even though he was harassed and threatened.
بالرغم من المضايقات والتهديدات .
His was a lonely struggle, because Bihar
صراعه كان فردياً، لأن بيهار
was also India's most corrupt state,
كانت أيضاً الولاية الأكثر فساداً في الهند،
where public officials were enriching themselves,
حيث كان الموظفون العموميّن يثرون أنفسهم ،
[rather] than serving the poor who had no means
بدلاً من خدمة الفقراء الذين لم يكن لهم أي سبيل
to express their anguish if their children
للتعبير عن كربهم حين يكون أطفالهم
had no food or no schooling.
بلا طعام وبلا تعليم
And I experienced this most viscerally
و قد مرت بي تجربة مماثلة هزت وجداني،
when I traveled to remote villages to study poverty.
عند تجوالي في القرى النائية لدراسة الفقر.
And as I went village to village,
أثناء تنقلي من قرية إلى أخرى،
I remember one day, when I was famished and exhausted,
أتذكر ذلك اليوم الذي كنت فيه جائعا جداً و منهكاً،
and I was almost collapsing
و كنت على وشك الإنهيار،
in a scorching heat under a tree,
في القيظ الحارق تحت شجرة،
and just at that time, one of the poorest men in that village
وفي تلك اللحظة، أحد أشد رجال القرية فقراً
invited me into his hut and graciously fed me.
دعاني إلى كوخه و أطعمني بكل كرم.
Only I later realized that what he fed me
أدركت ﻻحقاً أن ما أطعمني إياه
was food for his entire family for two days.
هو طعام أسرته كاملة ليومين.
This profound gift of generosity
هذا الكرم المتأصّل
challenged and changed the very purpose of my life.
تحدى و غيّر هدفي في الحياة.
I resolved to give back.
لقد أصبحت عازما على العطاء .
Later, I joined the World Bank, which sought to fight
فيما بعد، انضممت إلى البنك الدولي ، اللذي سعى لمكافحة
such poverty by transferring aid from rich to poor countries.
الفقر عن طريق تحويل المساعدات من الدول الغنية إلى الفقيرة.
My initial work focused on Uganda, where I focused
عملي المبدئي ركز على أوغندا، حيث ركزت
on negotiating reforms with the Finance Ministry of Uganda
في التفاوض على الإصلاحات مع وزارة المالية الأوغندية
so they could access our loans.
حتى يتمكنوا من الحصول على قروضنا .
But after we disbursed the loans, I remember
ولكن بعد صرف القروض، أتذكر
a trip in Uganda where I found newly built schools
وجدت في إحدى رحلاتي إلى أوغندا مدارس مبنية حديثا
without textbooks or teachers,
بدون كتب أو مدرسين،
new health clinics without drugs,
عيادات صحية جديدة بدون أدوية،
and the poor once again without any voice or recourse.
والفقراء مرة أخرى بدون صوت أو موارد.
It was Bihar all over again.
لقد كانت بيهار مرة أخرى.
Bihar represents the challenge of development:
بيهار مثلت تحدٍ في التنمية .
abject poverty surrounded by corruption.
فقر مدقع محاط بالفساد .
Globally, 1.3 billion people live on less than
عالميا، 1.3 مليار شخص يعيشون على أقل من
$1.25 a day, and the work I did in Uganda
دولار وربع لليوم ، والعمل الذي قمت به في أوغندا
represents the traditional approach to these problems
يمثل النهج التقليدي لحلّ هذه المشكلات
that has been practiced since 1944,
الذي يمارس منذ عام 1944،
when winners of World War II, 500 founding fathers,
حين جاء المنتصرون في الحرب العالمية الثانية، 500 أب مؤسس،
and one lonely founding mother,
و أمّ مؤسسة وحيدة،
gathered in New Hampshire, USA,
و اجتمعوا في نيو هامبشير، بالولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
to establish the Bretton Woods institutions,
لتأسيس مؤسسات مؤتمر بريتون وودس،
including the World Bank.
بما في ذلك البنك الدولي .
And that traditional approach to development
و ذلك النهج التقليدي في التنمية،
had three key elements. First, transfer of resources
يتكون من ثلاثة عناصر رئيسية، أوﻻ نقل المصادر
from rich countries in the North
من الدول الغنية في الشمال
to poorer countries in the South,
إلى الدول الفقيرة في الجنوب ،
accompanied by reform prescriptions.
مصحوبا بقائمة من الإصلاحات .
Second, the development institutions that channeled
ثانيا، مؤسسات التنمية التي وجهت
these transfers were opaque, with little transparency
عمليات النقل هذه كانت غامضة، وافتقرت إلى الشفافية
of what they financed or what results they achieved.
عن ما تمّ تمويله ، و ما هي النتائج التي حققوها.
And third, the engagement in developing countries
ثالثا، أن العمل في الدول النامية
was with a narrow set of government elites
كان مع فئة ضيقة من نخب الحكومة
with little interaction with the citizens, who are
بتفاعل قليل مع المواطنين ، الذين هم
the ultimate beneficiaries of development assistance.
المستفيدون النهائيين من المساعدات التنموية .
Today, each of these elements is opening up
اليوم ، كلّ من هذه العناصر في تفتح
due to dramatic changes in the global environment.
نتيجة للتغيّرات الكبيرة في المسرح العالمي.
Open knowledge, open aid, open governance,
المعرفة المفتوحة و المعونات المفتوحة و الإدارة المفتوحة،
and together, they represent three key shifts
كلّها مع بعضها تمثل ثلاثة تحوّلات أساسية
that are transforming development
التي حولت التنمية ،
and that also hold greater hope for the problems
والتي أيضا تحمل أماﻻً كبيرة للمشكلات
I witnessed in Uganda and in Bihar.
التي شهدتها في أوغندا وبيهار.
The first key shift is open knowledge.
أولى هذه التحوّلات الرئيسية هي المعرفة المفتوحة.
You know, developing countries today will not simply
كما تعرفون، أن الدول النامية اليوم لن تقبل ببساطة
accept solutions that are handed down to them
الحلول التي تعطى لهم
by the U.S., Europe or the World Bank.
عن طريق الوﻻيات المتحدة أو أوروبا أو البنك الدولي .
They get their inspiration, their hope,
هم يحصلون على إلهام وآمالهم
their practical know-how,
ومهاراتهم العملية،
from successful emerging economies in the South.
من نجاحات الاقتصادات الصاعدة في الجنوب .
They want to know how China lifted 500 million people
يريدون أن يعرفوا كيف استطاعت الصين رفع 500 مليون شخص
out of poverty in 30 years,
خارج حدود الفقر في 30 عام،
how Mexico's Oportunidades program
و كيف قام برنامج الفرص (أبارتونيدادس) المكسيكي
improved schooling and nutrition for millions of children.
بتحسين المستوى التعليمي والغذائي لملايين الأطفال .
This is the new ecosystem of open-knowledge flows,
هذا هو تيار النظام الإيكولوجي للمعرفة المفتوحة
not just traveling North to South, but South to South,
ﻻ ينتقل فقط من الشمال إلى الجنوب، ولكن من الجنوب إلى الجنوب،
and even South to North,
و حتى من الجنوب إلى الشمال،
with Mexico's Oportunidades today inspiring New York City.
حتى أن برنامج أبارتونيدادس المكسيكي اليوم يلهم مدينة نيويورك.
And just as these North-to-South transfers are opening up,
و مثلما تنفتح عمليات النقل من الشمال إلى الجنوب،
so too are the development institutions
كذلك تنفتح أيضا مؤسسات التنمية
that channeled these transfers.
التي توجّه عمليات النقل .
This is the second shift: open aid.
وهذا التحوّل الثاني : المعونة المفتوحة.
Recently, the World Bank opened its vault of data
مؤخرا، فتح البنك الدولي خزينته المعلوماتية
for public use, releasing 8,000 economic and social indicators
للاستخدام العام، مفرجا عن 8000 مؤشر اقتصادي واجتماعي
for 200 countries over 50 years,
لـ 200 بلد خلال 50 عاما ويزيد،
and it launched a global competition to crowdsource
مما أدى إلى تسابق عالمي لحشد المصادر
innovative apps using this data.
لتطبيقات مبتكرة باستخدام هذه المعلومات
Development institutions today are also opening
مؤسسات التنمية اليوم هي أيضا تفتح
for public scrutiny the projects they finance.
المشاريع التي تمولها للتدقيق العام.
Take GeoMapping. In this map from Kenya,
خذ رسم الخرائط الجغرافية. في هذه الخريطة من كينيا،
the red dots show where all the schools financed by donors
تظهر النقاط الحمراء جميع المدارس الممولة من الجهات المانحة
are located, and the darker the shade of green,
كلما زاد الظل الأخضر،
the more the number of out-of-school children.
كلما زاد عدد من الأطفال بدون مدارس.
So this simple mashup reveals that donors
يكشف هذا المزج البسيط أن الجهات المانحة
have not financed any schools in the areas
لم تمول أياً المدارس في المناطق
with the most out-of-school children,
التي يكثر فيها عدد اﻷطفال بدون مدارس
provoking new questions. Is development assistance
مما يثيرأسئلة جديدة. هل المساعدة الإنمائية
targeting those who most need our help?
تستهدف من هم الأكثر حاجة إلى مساعدتنا؟
In this manner, the World Bank has now GeoMapped
بهذه الطريقة، البنك الدولي لديه الآن رسم خرائط جغرافية
30,000 project activities in 143 countries,
لأنشطة 30,000 مشروع في 143 بلدا،
and donors are using a common platform
والجهات المانحة تستخدم منصة مشتركة
to map all their projects.
لتعيين كافة مشاريعها.
This is a tremendous leap forward in transparency
هذا قفزة هائلة إلى الأمام في مجال الشفافية
and accountability of aid.
والمسؤولية في المساعدة.
And this leads me to the third, and in my view,
وهذا يقودني إلى ثالث، وفي رأيي،
the most significant shift in development:
أهم تحول في التنمية:
open governance. Governments today are opening up
اﻹدارة المفتوحة. الحكومات اليوم تنفتح
just as citizens are demanding voice and accountability.
كما يطالب المواطنون بسماع أصواتهم وبالمساءلة.
From the Arab Spring to the Anna Hazare movement in India,
من الربيع العربي إلى حركة آنا هازار في الهند،
using mobile phones and social media
استخدام الهواتف النقالة والوسائط الاجتماعية
not just for political accountability
ليس فقط للمساءلة السياسية
but also for development accountability.
بل أيضاً للمساءلة النمو.
Are governments delivering services to the citizens?
هي الحكومات تقدم الخدمات للمواطنين؟
So for instance, several governments in Africa
لذا فعلى سبيل المثال، العديد من الحكومات في أفريقيا
and Eastern Europe are opening their budgets to the public.
وأوروبا الشرقية تفتح ميزانياتها للجمهور.
But, you know, there is a big difference between a budget
ولكن، كما تعلمون، هناك فرق كبير بين ميزانية
that's public and a budget that's accessible.
عامة وميزانية يمكن الوصول إليها.
This is a public budget. (Laughter)
هذه ميزانية عامة. (ضحك)
And as you can see, it's not really accessible
وكما ترون، إنها غير متاحة في الحقيقة
or understandable to an ordinary citizen
أو مفهومة لمواطن عادي
that is trying to understand how the government is spending its resources.
يحاول أن يفهم كيف تنفق الحكومة مواردها.
To tackle this problem, governments are using new tools
لمعالجة هذه المشكلة، تستخدم الحكومات أدوات جديدة
to visualize the budget so it's more understandable
لتصور الميزانية حتى تصبح أكثر قابلية للفهم
to the public.
للجمهور.
In this map from Moldova, the green color shows
في هذه الخريطة من مولدوفا، يظهر اللون الأخضر
those districts that have low spending on schools
تلك المناطق التي لديها إنفاق منخفض على المدارس
but good educational outcomes,
ولكن نتائج تعليمية جيدة،
and the red color shows the opposite.
واللون الأحمر يظهر عكس ذلك.
Tools like this help turn a shelf full of inscrutable documents
أدوات مثل هذه ساهمت في تحويل رف كامل من الوثائق الغامضة
into a publicly understandable visual,
إلى معلومات بصرية مفهومة للجمهور،
and what's exciting is that with this openness,
وما هو مثير أنه مع هذا الانفتاح،
there are today new opportunities for citizens
هنالك فرص جديدة للمواطنين اليوم
to give feedback and engage with government.
لإبداء الرأي والمشاركة مع الحكومة.
So in the Philippines today, parents and students
لذلك في الفلبين اليوم، الآباء والطلاب
can give real-time feedback on a website,
يمكنهم إبداء آراؤهم الواقعية على موقع
Checkmyschool.org, or using SMS, whether teachers
Checkmyschool.org، أو باستخدام الرسائل القصيرة، عما إذا كان المعلمون
and textbooks are showing up in school,
أو الكتب المدرسية متواجدة في المدرسة،
the same problems I witnessed in Uganda and in Bihar.
نفس المشاكل التي شهدتها في أوغندا وفي بيهار.
And the government is responsive. So for instance,
والحكومة تستجيب. لذا فعلى سبيل المثال،
when it was reported on this website that 800 students
عندما أفادت التقارير في هذا الموقع أن 800 طالب
were at risk because school repairs had stalled
معرضين للخطر لأنه الإصلاحات في المدرسة توقفت
due to corruption, the Department of Education
بسبب الفساد، وزارة التربية والتعليم
in the Philippines took swift action.
في الفلبين اتخذ إجراءات سريعة.
And you know what's exciting is that this innovation
أتعرفون ما هو مثير هو أن هذا الابتكار
is now spreading South to South, from the Philippines
ينتشر الآن من الجنوب إلى الجنوب، من الفلبين
to Indonesia, Kenya, Moldova and beyond.
لإندونيسيا، وكينيا، ومولدافيا، وأبعد من ذلك.
In Dar es Salaam, Tanzania, even an impoverished
في دار السلام، وتنزانيا، حتى أفقر
community was able to use these tools
المجتمعات كان قادراً على استخدام هذه الأدوات
to voice its aspirations.
للتعبير عن طموحاتها.
This is what the map of Tandale looked like
هكذا كانت تبدو خريطة تندلا
in August, 2011. But within a few weeks,
في آب/أغسطس، 2011. ولكن في غضون أسابيع قليلة،
university students were able to use mobile phones
طلاب الجامعة كانوا قادرين باستخدام الهواتف النقالة
and an open-source platform to dramatically map
ومنصة مفتوحة المصدر على تغيير خريطة بشكل كبير
the entire community infrastructure.
البنية التحتية للمجتمع بأسره.
And what is very exciting is that citizens were then
وما هو مثير جداً أن المواطنين أصبحوا حينها
able to give feedback as to which health or water points
قادرين على إعطاء معلوماتهم بشأن نقاط الصحة أو المياه
were not working, aggregated
التي لا تعمل، وتجميعها
in the red bubbles that you see,
في الفقاعات الحمراء التي ترونها،
which together provides a graphic visual
التي وفرت معا رسما بصريا
of the collective voices of the poor.
لأصوات الفقراء التجميعية.
Today, even Bihar is turning around and opening up
اليوم، حتى بيهار تدور وتتفتح
under a committed leadership that is making government
تحت قيادة ملتزمة تشكل حكومة
transparent, accessible and responsive to the poor.
شفافة ومتاحة وتستجيب للفقراء.
But, you know, in many parts of the world,
لكن، كما تعلمون، في أجزاء كثيرة من العالم،
governments are not interested in opening up
الحكومات ليست مهتمة في الانفتاح
or in serving the poor, and it is a real challenge
أو في خدمة الفقراء، وذلك تحدي حقيقي
for those who want to change the system.
لأولئك الذين يريدون تغيير النظام.
These are the lonely warriors
هؤﻻء هم المحاربون الوحيدون
like my father and many, many others,
مثل والدي وكثيرين كثيرين غيرهم،
and a key frontier of development work
والمفتاح الحدودي للعمل الإنمائي
is to help these lonely warriors join hands
هو مساعدة هؤلاء المحاربين الوحيدين في التكاتف
so they can together overcome the odds.
حتى يمكنهم التغلب على الصعاب معا.
So for instance, today, in Ghana, courageous reformers
على سبيل المثال، اليوم، في غانا، مصلحين شجعان
from civil society, Parliament and government,
من المجتمع المدني والبرلمان والحكومة،
have forged a coalition for transparent contracts
وقد أقامت تحالفا للعقود الشفافة
in the oil sector, and, galvanized by this,
في قطاع النفط، مدفوعين بهذا
reformers in Parliament are now investigating dubious contracts.
مصلحون في البرلمان الآن يحققون عقودا مشكوكٌ فيها.
These examples give new hope, new possibility
هذه الأمثلة تعطي أملا جديداً، وإمكانيات جديدة
to the problems I witnessed in Uganda
للمشاكل التي شهدت في أوغندا
or that my father confronted in Bihar.
أو التي واجهها والدي في بيهار.
Two years ago, on April 8th, 2010, I called my father.
قبل عامين، في 8 أبريل 2010، اتصلت بوالدي.
It was very late at night, and at age 80,
كان الوقت متأخر جداً في الليل، وفي سن ال 80،
he was typing a 70-page public interest litigation
كان يكتب ترافع دعوى مصلحة عامة من 70 صفحة
against corruption in a road project.
ضد الفساد في مشروع طرق.
Though he was no lawyer, he argued the case in court
وهو ليس بمحام، قام بمحاجّة القضية في المحكمة
himself the next day. He won the ruling,
بنفسه في اليوم التالي. وقد فاز بالحكم،
but later that very evening,
ولكن في وقت لاحق ذلك المساء،
he fell, and he died.
سقط، وفارق الحياة.
He fought till the end, increasingly passionate
لقد حارب حتى النهاية، بعاطفة جياشة
that to combat corruption and poverty,
في مكافحة الفساد والفقر،
not only did government officials need to be honest,
ﻻ يلزم فقط أن يكون المسئولون الحكوميون صادقين،
but citizens needed to join together
يجب على المواطنين أن يساندوا بعضهم
to make their voices heard.
لجعل أصواتهم مسموعة.
These became the two bookends of his life,
أصبحت هذه حدوده في الحياة
and the journey he traveled in between
والرحلة التي سافر فيها بين ذلك
mirrored the changing development landscape.
عكست التغير في مشهد التطور
Today, I'm inspired by these changes, and I'm excited
اليوم، وأستمد إلهامي من هذه التغييرات، وأنا متحمس
that at the World Bank, we are embracing
أننا في البنك الدولي، ونعتنق
these new directions, a significant departure
هذه الاتجاهات الجديدة، فارق كبير
from my work in Uganda 20 years ago.
عن عملي في أوغندا قبل 20 عاماً.
We need to radically open up development
ونحن بحاجة إلى الانفتاح جذريا في التنمية
so knowledge flows in multiple directions,
حتى تتدفق المعرفة في اتجاهات متعددة،
inspiring practitioners, so aid becomes transparent,
فتُلهِم الممارسين، وتصبح المعونات شفافة،
accountable and effective, so governments open up
مسؤولة وفعالة، حينها تفتح الحكومات
and citizens are engaged and empowered
والمواطنين يشاركون ويُمكننون
with reformers in government.
في الإصلاحات مع الحكومة.
We need to accelerate these shifts.
نحن بحاجة إلى تعجيل هذه التحولات.
If we do, we will find that the collective voices
وإذا فعلنا ذلك، سوف نجد أن الأصوات الجماعية
of the poor will be heard in Bihar,
للفقراء في ولاية بيهار مسموعة،
in Uganda, and beyond.
في أوغندا، وأبعد من ذلك.
We will find that textbooks and teachers
وسوف نجد أن الكتب المدرسية والمدرسين
will show up in schools for their children.
سوف يظهرون في المدارس لأطفالهم.
We will find that these children, too,
أننا سوف نجد أن هؤلاء الأطفال، أيضا،
have a real chance of breaking their way out of poverty.
لهم فرصة حقيقية في كسر طريقهم نحو الخروج من الفقر.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)